<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <monster>
        <name>SergiusArimano</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>neutral evil</alignment>
        <ac>14 (leather armor)</ac>
        <hp>18 (3d8+3)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>9</str>
        <dex>16</dex>
        <con>13</con>
        <int>15</int>
        <wis>14</wis>
        <cha>11</cha>
        <senses>passive Perception 14</senses>
        <languages>Common, Elvish, Thieves' Cant</languages>
        <cr>1</cr>
        <trait>
            <name>Expertise</name>
            <text>Stealth, Investigation (double bonus already included)</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Sneak Attack (2d6)</name>
            <text>once per turn, extra damage if he has advantage or an ally is adjacent to the target</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Cunning Action</name>
            <text>bonus action: Dash, Disengage, or Hide</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Assassinate</name>
            <text>advantage on attack rolls against creatures that haven't acted yet. Automatic critical hit against surprised creatures.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Ring of Shadows (magic item)</name>
            <text>can cast *Invisibility* (on self) 1/day. Doesn't require concentration but ends if he attacks or casts a spell.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger (melee/ranged)</name>
            <text>Attack: +5, melee 5ft / 1sq or ranged 20ft / 4sq — 60ft / 12sq Damage: 1d4+3 piercing (+2d6 Sneak Attack if applicable)</text>
            <attack>Dagger (melee/ranged)|+5|1d4+3</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Hand Crossbow (ranged)</name>
            <text>Attack: +5, ranged 30ft / 6sq — 120ft / 24sq Damage: 1d6+3 piercing (+2d6 Sneak Attack if applicable)</text>
            <attack>Hand Crossbow (ranged)|+5|1d6+3</attack>
        </action>
        <description>The Sergio of Boris: a schemer, underhanded, pulling strings behind the scenes. Former owner of &quot;L'Immane Alabarda,&quot; he sold vigor potions and personalized erotic portraits to the nobles of Fianus. The Count was an excellent client — he had an &quot;artistic&quot; portrait commissioned that he never paid for. The Count's wife (a prude) discovered everything and had the &quot;Gabella Pudicitiae&quot; imposed on all risqué merchandise. Marchese Arimano went from legitimate merchant to smuggler, and now he's getting his revenge.
He fortuitously found the Count's Ring in the sewers and uses it as the instrument of an elaborate revenge — a public treasure hunt that humiliates the Count. He still has the unpaid portrait and uses it as leverage.
Extremely intelligent, always three steps ahead of everyone. Speaks little, smiles a lot — the smile of someone who knows something you don't. Doesn't get his hands dirty if he can avoid it. Vain about his cunning: he leaves clues because he wants people to know it was him. The double S is his signature — ego disguised as anonymity.
**Master of disguise:** regularly disguises himself as Terzilio the greengrocer (and others). Has a network of informants in the village (Varys/GOT type). Possesses a magical invisibility item. Sometimes the PCs talk to him without knowing it.
Role: hidden antagonist</description>
    </monster>
</compendium>