<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <monster>
        <name>Guardian of Lumina</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (construct (stone golem))</type>
        <alignment>neutral (corrupted by vecna)</alignment>
        <ac>17</ac>
        <hp>50 (of 178 maximum — heavily wounded)</hp>
        <speed>10 ft.</speed>
        <str>22</str>
        <dex>9</dex>
        <con>20</con>
        <int>3</int>
        <wis>11</wis>
        <cha>1</cha>
        <cr>5</cr>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Immunity to Non-Magical Weapons</name>
            <text>immune to damage from non-magical or non-silvered weapons</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Corruption Aura (only if corrupted)</name>
            <text>each creature within 3m / 10ft / 2qd must make a Constitution save DC 14 at the start of its turn or take 5 (1d10) necrotic damage</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Fist (melee)</name>
            <text>Attack: +8, reach 1.5m / 5ft / 1qd Damage: 3d8+6 bludgeoning</text>
            <attack>Fist (melee)|+8|3d8+6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Dark Burst (1/combat, only if corrupted)</name>
            <text>Range: 4.5m / 15ft / 3qd Saving Throw: Dexterity DC 15 Failure: 3d8+6 necrotic damage Success: half damage</text>
        </action>
        <description>A huge crouching stone golem, clearly wounded — deep cracks run through its body and stone fragments are missing from its torso and arms. It was a sacred guardian of the Temple of Lumina, now pervaded by Vecna's dark influence. An aura of necromantic energy surrounds it.
It does not speak except in single words and monosyllables. It has a rough understanding of human language, not intelligent enough to hold a conversation. It recognizes bearers of the Scepter and their companions as friends and defends them from anyone who claims to want to take it from them.
Role: temple guardian, potential ally</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>AxelRuby</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>chaotic evil</alignment>
        <ac>11 (leather armor)</ac>
        <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>15</str>
        <dex>11</dex>
        <con>14</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>11</cha>
        <senses>Passive Perception 10</senses>
        <languages>any one (usually Common)</languages>
        <cr>1/2</cr>
        <description>A massive man, arms covered in arena scars. Square jaw, nose broken multiple times, small calculating eyes that betray an intelligence his physique doesn't suggest. He wears a studded leather vest over a worn shirt and a rough ruby hanging from his neck — the gang's symbol.
He speaks little and in a low voice, forcing his interlocutors to lean in. When he laughs, it's a short, unpleasant sound. He has a habit of cracking his knuckles before making a decision.
Distinctive trait: brutal and cunning in equal measure. He's not the stupid brute he appears to be — he's a seasoned smuggler who learned to survive in the arena and on the streets.
Role: leader of the Ruby gang (east Orcastle)</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>BrotherThaddeus</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>lawful good</alignment>
        <ac>10</ac>
        <hp>1</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>10</cha>
        <cr>1</cr>
        <description>An elderly man, thin, with calloused hands of someone who has worked his entire life. Shaved head, short white beard. He still wears the insignia of the order of Tyr — a **stylized severed hand** embroidered on his tunic — despite having left the order. He says he wears it &quot;to remember what it should have been, not what it became.&quot;
He speaks with a calm and measured voice, choosing his words carefully. He has the gaze of someone who has seen too much and decided not to look away. He drinks herbal teas, never alcohol.
Distinctive trait: disarming honesty. He tells the truth even when it would be more convenient to lie — and that's precisely what makes him hard to believe.
Role: informant, former disciple of Tyr</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>FrankiePartenope</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>chaotic neutral</alignment>
        <ac>16 (Unarmored Defense: 10 + DEX +3 + CON +3)</ac>
        <hp>47 (5d12 + 15)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>20</str>
        <dex>16</dex>
        <con>16</con>
        <int>8</int>
        <wis>18</wis>
        <cha>8</cha>
        <cr>4</cr>
        <action>
            <name>#</name>
            <text/>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Battleaxe (melee)</name>
            <text>Attack: +8 Damage: 1d10+5 slashing</text>
            <attack>Battleaxe (melee)|+8|1d10+5</attack>
        </action>
        <description>A former adventurer with an imposing physique, Frankie is a people's hero — a sort of local Robin Hood. He carries himself proudly despite the scars and marks of imprisonment in Orcastle. He speaks in a direct tone, no frills, and has a visceral hatred for Lord Malebranche that seeps from every word.
Distinctive trait: he still bears the marks of the explosive collar on his neck — a band of reddened skin he touches constantly, as if to remind himself he's no longer a prisoner.
Role: allied NPC of the party</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>HelmutVanHeuten</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>lawful good</alignment>
        <ac>10</ac>
        <hp>1</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>10</cha>
        <cr>1</cr>
        <description>Helmut Van Heuten is a wealthy and respected merchant, in his sixties, with a well-groomed white beard and fine but unpretentious clothing. He always wears a ring with the symbol of Tyr — a set of scales — and has the habit of offering hot tea to anyone who sits in his study. He has scribe's hands, not a warrior's, and a calm, gentle voice that inspires trust.
He is courteous, methodical, and genuinely devout. He is not an adventurer and doesn't pretend to be — he knows his role is to provide resources, not to wield swords.
Role: secondary</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>KreigHighlander</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>lawful neutral</alignment>
        <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
        <hp>52 (8d8+16)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>16</str>
        <dex>11</dex>
        <con>14</con>
        <int>11</int>
        <wis>11</wis>
        <cha>15</cha>
        <senses>Passive Perception 10</senses>
        <languages>any one (usually Common)</languages>
        <cr>3</cr>
        <description>A tall and imposing man, military bearing even when seated. Short-cropped gray hair, groomed beard, a thin scar crossing his left temple. He always wears polished plate armor — even when it's not needed. Dark blue cloak with the Highlander crest: a falcon on a mountain background.
He speaks with a booming voice, accustomed to giving orders and being obeyed. He looks down on his interlocutors — literally and figuratively. He has a habit of drumming his fingers on his sword hilt when bored.
Distinctive trait: arrogant and overconfident to a fault. He systematically underestimates his opponents — a flaw that could cost him dearly.
Role: leader of the Castro (center of Orcastle); Count Wildforge in Module D</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Kurzum</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
        <alignment>lawful evil</alignment>
        <ac>17 (splint armor)</ac>
        <hp>58 (9d8+18)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>16</str>
        <dex>13</dex>
        <con>14</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>11</wis>
        <cha>10</cha>
        <senses>Passive Perception 12</senses>
        <languages>any one (usually Common)</languages>
        <cr>3</cr>
        <description>Kurzum is the owner of the *Giavellotto Fantasma*, a weapons shop that also serves as a reference point for those seeking unorthodox jobs. She has hard features, dark calculating eyes, and a thin scar crossing her left eyebrow. She wears a leather apron over a light chain shirt — always ready, even behind the counter.
She speaks little and chooses her words with surgical precision. She almost never smiles, and when she does it's worse. She has a habit of cleaning a weapon while talking to customers — a gesture that is never casual.
Role: secondary</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>LordMalebranche</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>lawful evil</alignment>
        <ac>15 (Mage Armor)</ac>
        <hp>99 (18d8 + 18)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>12</con>
        <int>20</int>
        <wis>15</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <senses>Passive Perception 12</senses>
        <languages>Common, Draconic, Infernal, Abyssal</languages>
        <cr>12</cr>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Corrupt Will</name>
            <text>when Malebranche deals necrotic damage, he regains temporary HP equal to half the damage dealt</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Legendary Actions (3/round)</name>
            <text>Malebranche can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the following. Only one at a time, at the end of another creature's turn.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Cantrip (1 action)</name>
            <text>casts a cantrip</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Rapid Summoning (2 actions)</name>
            <text>summons 1d4 skeletons (CR 1/4) in unoccupied spaces within 9m / 30ft</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Life Drain (1 action)</name>
            <text>a creature within 9m / 30ft must succeed on a Constitution save DC 17 or take 2d8 necrotic damage. Malebranche regains HP equal to the damage dealt.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Necrotic Ray (ranged)</name>
            <text>Attack: +9, range 36m / 120ft / 24qd Damage: 3d10 necrotic</text>
            <attack>Necrotic Ray (ranged)|+9|3d10</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Corrupt governor of Orcastle, Lord Malebranche is a thin, pale man with sunken eyes that seem to calculate the value of every person in the room. He wears dark noble garments with silver embroidery. His hands are always cold — a side effect of the necromantic magic he practices.
Distinctive trait: he speaks with impeccable courtesy even when ordering atrocities. He never raises his voice. His calm is more unsettling than any threat.
Role: main antagonist</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>LudmillaDawnshield</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>neutral good</alignment>
        <ac>10</ac>
        <hp>1</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>10</cha>
        <cr>1</cr>
        <description>Ludmilla Dawnshield is just over twenty but carries the experience of someone who grew up among nautical charts and tales of lost lands. Short-cropped brown hair for practicality, skin tanned by sun and sea wind, bright attentive eyes. She wears sturdy travel clothes and always wears a medallion around her neck with the **family crest**: a set of scales superimposed on a sea wave.
She speaks with enthusiasm when it comes to exploration and history, but becomes serious and measured when the conversation touches on her family or Svoalbard. She has a quiet determination that makes her reliable in critical moments.
Role: ally</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>MalachiasOmbrascura</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (dragonborn)</type>
        <alignment>to be determined in play</alignment>
        <ac>13 (chain shirt)</ac>
        <hp>27 (5d8 + 5)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>12</con>
        <int>13</int>
        <wis>16</wis>
        <cha>13</cha>
        <senses>Passive Perception 13</senses>
        <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
        <cr>2</cr>
        <trait>
            <name>Breath Weapon</name>
            <text>once per short rest, 4.5m / 15ft / 3qd cone. Dexterity save DC 11, 2d6 damage (type depends on lineage — to be defined).</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Divine Eminence</name>
            <text>as a bonus action, can grant a creature within 9m / 30ft a 1d4 bonus to an attack roll or saving throw (3 uses/day).</text>
        </trait>
        <description>A dragonborn with a subdued air who goes by Elemir Strunz to hide his true identity. He blends in among Axel Ruby's followers in the East zone, trying to go unnoticed. He has a star-shaped scar on his left calf — a mark that could betray him if someone knows what to look for.
Distinctive trait: he speaks little and chooses his words carefully. When he lies, he tends to touch his left calf — a tell that attentive players can notice.
Role: ambiguous allied NPC</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>MesusuMercone</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
        <alignment>lawful neutral</alignment>
        <ac>16 (chain shirt, shield)</ac>
        <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>13</str>
        <dex>12</dex>
        <con>12</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>11</wis>
        <cha>10</cha>
        <senses>Passive Perception 12</senses>
        <languages>any one (usually Common)</languages>
        <cr>1/8</cr>
        <description>Mesusu Mercone is the captain of the flying ship *Airborne*. Short and stocky as expected of a dwarf, she wears her hair in tight braids under a reinforced leather helm. She has sailor's calloused hands and a voice that cuts through the headwind without needing to shout. She wears a worn but clean military jacket with the Airborne insignia sewn on the shoulder.
She speaks directly, no frills. She doesn't waste time with pleasantries but isn't rude — simply efficient. She has a habit of drumming her fingers on her sword pommel when someone talks too much.
Role: secondary</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>MirandaEmerald</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>lawful evil</alignment>
        <ac>12</ac>
        <hp>27 (6d8)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>15</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>14</int>
        <wis>14</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <senses>Passive Perception 14</senses>
        <languages>Common, Elvish</languages>
        <cr>1</cr>
        <trait>
            <name>Sneak Attack (1/turn)</name>
            <text>+2d6 extra damage if she has advantage or an ally in melee with the target</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Cunning Action</name>
            <text>Dash, Disengage, or Hide as a bonus action</text>
        </trait>
        <description>A slender woman, sharp features, black hair pulled back in a tight braid. Green eyes — the same color as the emerald she wears as a brooch on her cloak. She dresses with understated elegance, always in black and dark green. Her hands are well-kept, nails short — a scholar's hands, not a fighter's.
She speaks with measured calm, every word chosen with surgical precision. She never raises her voice. She rarely smiles, and when she does it's a smile that doesn't reach her eyes.
Distinctive trait: cold and calculating. She never acts on impulse. Every move is planned three steps ahead.
Role: leader of the Emerald gang (west Orcastle)</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>OrlommGlittergear</name>
        <size>S</size>
        <type>humanoid (gnome)</type>
        <alignment>neutral good</alignment>
        <ac>10</ac>
        <hp>1</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>10</cha>
        <cr>1</cr>
        <description>An enthusiastic and curious gnome, famous for having navigated unknown routes. Short even for a gnome, with lively eyes and a short beard always ruffled by the wind. He speaks quickly and gets excited about anything — a new route, an approaching storm, a sea monster on the horizon. For him, everything is an adventure.
Role: captain of the ship La Nuova Speranza</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>OthranVorash</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (half-elf)</type>
        <alignment>neutral evil</alignment>
        <ac>15 (reinforced light chain shirt + DEX)</ac>
        <hp>84</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>16</dex>
        <con>14</con>
        <int>14</int>
        <wis>11</wis>
        <cha>18</cha>
        <senses>darkvision 18m</senses>
        <languages>Common, Elvish</languages>
        <cr>9</cr>
        <action>
            <name>#</name>
            <text/>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger (melee/ranged)</name>
            <text>Attack: +6 Damage: 1d4+3 piercing</text>
            <attack>Dagger (melee/ranged)|+6|1d4+3</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Othran is a half-elf with an elegant bearing and a calculating gaze. The elven traits are barely hinted at — slightly pointed ears, sharp features — but his eyes have an unnatural light, a greenish reflection that betrays the pact with Vecna. He dresses in dark, practical clothing, without ostentation.
Distinctive trait: he speaks in a low, measured tone, as if every conversation were an interrogation. He has a habit of staring at people in silence before answering — a trick to make them uncomfortable.
Role: recurring antagonist</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>SirAlaric</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>lawful evil (disguised as lawful neutral)</alignment>
        <ac>15 (Mage Armor)</ac>
        <hp>90 (12d8 + 36)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>16</con>
        <int>18</int>
        <wis>14</wis>
        <cha>12</cha>
        <cr>1</cr>
        <description>Sir Alaric presents himself as an austere and devout man, with short-cropped gray hair and clear eyes that convey authority. He wears the ceremonial robes of the Keepers of the Balance with a naturalness that inspires trust. His voice is calm, measured — every word seems weighed and just.
Beneath the facade, Alaric is a man consumed by ambition. His eyes betray a greed that no prayer can hide, if you know where to look.
Distinctive trait: he has a habit of clasping his hands as if in prayer when he speaks — a gesture his followers find reassuring, but which is actually a nervous tic that betrays the calculation behind every word.
Role: antagonist</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>SirAldric</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human (sword wraith))</type>
        <alignment>lawful neutral</alignment>
        <ac>18 (spectral armor)</ac>
        <hp>127 (15d8 + 60)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>18</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>18</con>
        <int>11</int>
        <wis>12</wis>
        <cha>14</cha>
        <senses>darkvision 18m / 60ft, Passive Perception 14</senses>
        <languages>Common</languages>
        <cr>8</cr>
        <trait>
            <name>Partial Incorporeality</name>
            <text>Sir Aldric can move through creatures and objects as difficult terrain. He takes 5 (1d10) force damage if he ends his turn inside an object.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Command Aura (9m / 30ft)</name>
            <text>allied undead within the aura have advantage on attack rolls.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Guardian's Will</name>
            <text>if reduced to 0 HP, he can make a Constitution save DC 10 (+1 for each time after the first). On a success, he returns to 1 HP.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Spectral Greatsword (melee)</name>
            <text>Attack: +7, reach 1.5m / 5ft / 1qd Damage: 2d6+4 slashing + 2d6 necrotic</text>
            <attack>Spectral Greatsword (melee)|+7|2d6+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Sir Aldric makes two attacks with the Spectral Greatsword.</text>
        </action>
        <description>Sir Aldric is a warrior transformed into a vengeful spirit. He appears as an ethereal figure with a pale face and melancholic eyes, wrapped in spectral armor that emanates a cold, bluish light. His sword is incorporeal but cuts like steel. He embodies the boundary between sacredness and unease — a guardian who didn't choose his fate but accepts it with solemnity.
Distinctive trait: he speaks with a cavernous, measured voice, like a judge who has already passed sentence. He is not hostile by nature — he is hostile by duty.
Role: guardian of the Golden Brooch of Ostegard</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>ZalharaLorenn</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>neutral evil</alignment>
        <ac>12</ac>
        <hp>27 (6d8)</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>15</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>12</int>
        <wis>14</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <senses>Passive Perception 16</senses>
        <languages>any two</languages>
        <cr>1</cr>
        <description>A middle-aged woman, anonymous and reassuring in appearance — exactly as she wants. Brown hair pulled back, round glasses, modest but clean scholar's clothing. She always carries a leather bag full of scrolls and books. She speaks in a calm, cultured tone, citing sacred texts of Tyr with ease.
Around her neck she wears a ring on a chain — the **Ring of the Evanescent Shadow**. If anyone asks, she says it's a family heirloom. The ring bears an inscription: *&quot;turn left.&quot;*
Distinctive trait: she is so convincing in her role as a scholar that even Tyr's priests find her credible. Her best weapon is the trust she inspires.
Role: spy in service of Vecna</description>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Zikle</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (goblin)</type>
        <alignment>chaotic neutral</alignment>
        <ac>10</ac>
        <hp>1</hp>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>10</cha>
        <cr>1</cr>
        <description>In life, Zikle was a goblin wizard of extraordinary power — small in stature but immense in intellect and ambition. As a wraith, he appears as a translucent greenish shadow with still-recognizable goblinoid features: pointed ears, sunken eyes that glow with a cold spectral light, skeletal hands that move as if still tracing arcane formulas in the air.
His voice is a hoarse, metallic whisper, interrupted by sudden bursts of rage. He alternates between moments of brilliant lucidity and blind fury — the betrayal that killed him still consumes him.
Role: secondary</description>
    </monster>
</compendium>
